Hohenberger mss., 1917-1960 LMC 2197
Lilly Library
Hohenberger mss.
1917-1960
Lilly Library
Hohenberger, Frank M. (Frank Michael), 1876-1963
LMC 2197
49 Boxes
The Hohenberger mss., 1917-1960, consist primarily of photographs by Frank Michael Hohenberger, 1876-1963, Brown County photographer and newspaperman.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Hohenberger was born in Ohio in 1876 and orphaned at five years of age. He spent his boyhood as a printing apprentice and later worked several years on newspapers in Dayton, Ohio, Louisville, Kentucky, and finally for the Indianapolis Star. In 1917 he left Indianapolis to start a small photography business in Nashville, Indiana, concentrating on the subject matter of Brown County. The next forty-seven years were spent recording the life, customs, and scenes of the hills of Brown County, with side trips and hired assignments in other areas of Indiana, Kentucky, South Carolina, and Mexico. From 1923 to 1954 he wrote a column for the Sunday Indianapolis Star, "Down in the Hills O' Brown County." The articles were frequently illustrated with his photographs. Hohenberger, who died in November 1963, willed his collection to the Indiana University Foundation. The collection is housed in, and administered by, the Lilly Library, Indiana University.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into the following series: Safety Negatives, Prints and Positives, Personal, Correspondence, Notes and Writings, Newspaper Clippings, D. Bailey Materials, and Miscellaneous.
Scope and Content Note
The photograph collection totals 8300 prints and 9400 negatives. Also present in the collection is a small amount of correspondence, a lengthy "diary" by Hohenberger describing many of his photographic tours and processes, and copies of his "Down in the Hills O' Brown County" articles. A few works of art on paper by Beatrice S. Levy, Carl C. Graf, Louis Oscar Griffith, and John Moranz complete the collection.
Among the correspondents are Rossa Belle Cooley, Arthur Wells Elting, Kate Gleason, Don Herold, William M. Herschel, James R. Hopkins, Horace Kephart, Elfrieda Lang, Richard Lieber, James Arthur Stuart, Webb Waldron, Thomas Jackson Woofter, and Carolina Bleach.
Note on Indexing Term - "Art": There are photographs of artists and their artworks. Also included are an etching by Beatrice Levy; a pen and ink sketch by Carl C. Graf; a pencil sketch by Louis Oscar Griffith and a print of an etching by John Moranz.
Note on Indexing Term - "Religion": Of particular interest are the many images of churches.
Note on Indexing Term - "West (U.S.)" and "Americana": Of particular interest are a group of photographs of western states from 1952. Included are views of the Grand Canyon, Indian cliff dwellings, and adobe churches.
For digitized photographs, see the Frank M. Hohenberger Photograph Collection.
Acquisition Information
Transfer: 1998
Related Materials
See Hohenberger mss. II, also at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Art; Religion; Americana; West (U.S.); photography; Indiana; Brown County, Indiana; Hohenberger, Frank M. (Frank Michael), 1876-1963
- Personal
  - Diary, 1917-1923 (Box 1)
  - Diary, 1923-1957 (Box 1)
  - Diary (xeroxed copy), p. 1-99 (Box 1)
  - Diary (xeroxed copy), p. 100-199 (Box 1)
  - Diary (xeroxed copy), p. 200-299 (Box 1)
  - Diary (xeroxed copy), p. 300-399 (Box 1)
  - Diary (xeroxed copy), p. 400-499 (Box 1)
  - Diary (xeroxed copy), p. 500-573 (Box 1)
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1919-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1960 (Box 1)
  - Undated, A-Z (Box 1)
- Notes and Writings
  - Writings (Box 1)
  - Notes for negatives (Box 1)
  - Manuscript index cards (Box 1)
- Newspaper Clippings
  - 1923-1925, Sept. 12 (Box 1)
  - 1925, Sept. 20-1954 (Box 2)
  - By others, 1901-1946; 3 Folders (Box 2)
  - Undated, A-Z
    - Alabama (Box 3)
    - Animals and Insects (Box 3)
    - Artists (Box 3)
    - Bridges (Box 3)
    - Brown County, Indiana (Box 3)
    - Brown Murder Case (Box 3)
    - Canals (Box 3)
    - Cuba (Box 3)
    - Florida (Box 3)
    - Flowers and Trees (Box 3)
    - Georgia (Box 3)
    - Indiana (Box 3)
    - Indiana University (Box 3)
    - Indy 500 (Box 3)
    - Kentucky (Box 3)
    - Log Building (Box 3)
    - Louisiana (Box 3)
    - Mexico (Box 3)
    - Mills (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Mississippi (Box 3)
    - New England (Box 3)
    - New Mexico (Box 3)
    - North Carolina (Box 3)
    - Ohio (Box 3)
    - People (Box 3)
    - Railroads (Box 3)
    - Snow scenes (Box 3)
    - South Carolina (Box 3)
    - Tennessee (Box 3)
    - Texas (Box 3)
    - Virginia (Box 3)
    - Wallace, Lew (Box 3)
- D. Bailey Materials
  - The Nashville Observer xeroxed copies (Box 3)
  - "Chronology of Newspapers in Brown County" (Box 3)
  - "A Century of Service: A Brief History of the Newspapers of Brown County Indiana," Bob Cramer (reprinted from the Brown County Democrat) (Box 3)
  - "The Museum Complex of the Brown County Historical Society," Dorothy B. Bailey, 1976 (Box 3)
  - "Chronology of Newspapers in Brown County" (Box 3)
  - "County of Brown, Indiana - Historical and Biographical," Weston A. Goodspeed, ed. Charles Blanchard, 1884 (1972 facsimile by Brown County Historical Society) (Box 3)
  - "Brown County, Indiana Cemeteries" (Box 3)
- Typed index to collection, 3 Folders (Box 3)
- Index and processing notes (Box 3)
- Drawings, etc. by Carl C. Graf, Louis O. Griffith, Beatrice S. Levy, and John Moranz (Box 4)
- Contact Prints and Positives
  - Color Transparencies
    - Brown County (Box 4)
    - Western States, '52 (Box 5)
  - Contact Prints by Subject (Various Sizes)
    - Birds, animals (Box 4)
    - Blossoming trees and shrubs (Box 4)
    - Canada, 1955 / Christian Church fire, 1931 / Clouds (Box 4)
    - Cuba '41 (Box 4)
    - Derk Smit (Box 5)
    - Flowers, wild & garden (Box 7)
    - Fruits, nuts, vegetables (Box 4)
    - Hanover / Hilltop (Box 4)
    - I.U. negs. 101-200 (Box 6)
    - I.U. negs. 1-100 (Box 6)
    - I.U. negs. 201-290 (Box 6)
    - I.U. negs. 291-377 (Box 6)
    - I.U. negs. 378- (Box 6)
    - Indiana, copies / Indiana University (Box 4)
    - Kentucky '33 (Box 4)
    - Kentucky '38 (Box 4)
    - Mardi Gras '38 (Box 4)
    - Mexico '39 1-130 (Box 7)
    - Mexico '40 131-254 (Box 7)
    - Mexico '49 / Mexico '54 (Box 7)
    - Mexico COPIES (Box 7)
    - Nashville Realty (Box 7)
    - Navy trip (Box 7)
    - New England '48, 1-28 (5x7), 29-35 (4x5) (Box 7)
    - New Mexico '42 (Box 7)
    - North Carolina '39 (Box 7)
    - Paintings COPIES (Box 7)
    - Portraits and groups 1926-1946 (Box 7)
    - Portraits and Groups 1947-1957 (Box 7)
    - Portraits and Groups II (Box 5)
    - Shulz, Ada & Adolph / Shulz, Adolph (Box 5)
    - South Carolina '29 (Box 5)
    - South Carolina '38 (Box 5)
    - Southeastern states '47 (2 1/2 x 2 1/2) (Box 48)
    - Southeastern states '47, 1-32 (5x7), 33-49 (4x5) (Box 5)
    - State Library (Box 5)
    - T.C. Steele / Thomson estate / Wallace/Riley (Box 48)
    - Washington, Ky. / Wendel / Western States (Box 5)
    - Winter '25-'42 (Box 5)
    - Winter '42-'46 (#1-79) (Box 5)
    - Winter '42-'46 (#80-140) (Box 5)
    - Winter '47-'52 (Box 6)
    - Winter, n.d. / Unindexed (Box 6)
  - 3" x 4" - 1292 contact prints, (9 boxes) (Box 8)
  - 3 1/4" x 4 1/4" - contact prints, (1 box) (Box 8)
  - 3" x 5" - 204 contact prints, (2 boxes) (Box 8)
  - 4" x 5" - contact prints and positives, (13 boxes)
    - 1-43 (Box 9)
    - Plates (Box 10)
  - 5" x 7" - contact prints and positives, (22 boxes)
    - 1-76 (Box 10)
    - 77-100 (Box 11)
    - Plates (Box 11)
    - Copies (Box 11)
  - 8" x 10" - 1260 positives, (6 boxes) (Box 12)
- Safety Negatives
  - 3" x 4" - 1292 negatives, (22 boxes) (Box 13, Box 14)
  - 3 1/4" x 4 1/4" - negatives, (1 box) (Box 15)
  - 3" x 5" - 204 negatives, (5 boxes) (Box 15)
  - 4" x 5" - negatives, (20 boxes) (Box 15, Box 16, Box 17)
  - Plate negatives and autochromes, (14 boxes, 9 folders) (Box 28-30)
  - 5" x 7" - negatives, (41 boxes) (Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 31)
  - 8" x 10" - 1260 negatives, (9 boxes) (Box 26, Box 27)
  - Various sizes - duplicate negatives, (10 boxes) (Box 28-30)
  - Various sizes - negatives grouped by subject, (74 boxes) (Box 20-25, Box 31)
- Print Boxes
  Arrangement
  This series has been reboxed. Previous box numbers are retained for continuity with historical requests.
  - Animals, birds, insects (Print Box 1) (Box 32)
  - Apple blossoms, cornfields (Print Box 2) (Box 32)
  - Artists--portraits, studios, galleries, A-Sm (Print Box 3) (Box 32)
  - Artists--portraits, studios, galleries, Sn-Z (Print Box 3) (Box 33)
  - Autographed by Hohenberger (Print Box 4) (Box 33)
  - Beech trees, sunsets, moonlight (Print Box 5) (Box 33)
  - Berries, vegetables, fruits (Print Box 6) (Box 33)
  - Bridges (Print Box 7) (Box 33)
  - Bridges (cont.) (Print Box 7) (Box 34)
  - Brown County (Print Box 8) (Box 34)
  - Brown County--8x10 (Print Box 9) (Box 34)
  - Character studies (Print Box 10) (Box 35)
  - Clouds, trees (Print Box 11) (Box 35)
  - Circus (Print Box 12) (Box 35)
  - Copies--paintings, art objects (Print Box 13) (Box 35)
  - Copies--paintings, art objects (cont.) (Print Box 13) (Box 36)
  - Enlargements (Print Box 14) (Box 36)
  - Flowers, blossoming trees (Print Box 15) (Box 36)
  - Flowers, blossoming trees (cont.) (Print Box 15) (Box 37)
  - Liars' bench (Print Box 16) (Box 37)
  - Indiana--scenes, historic, monuments (Print Box 17) (Box 37)
  - Indiana University (Print Box 18) (Box 37)
  - Interiors (Print Box 19) (Box 38)
  - Landscapes (Print Boxes 20-21) (Box 38)
  - Landscapes, with water (Print Box 22) (Box 39)
  - Lincoln and Kentucky (Print Box 23) (Box 39)
  - Log structures--homes, log jail (Print Box 24) (Box 39)
  - Log structures--churches, schools, cabins (Print Box 24) (Box 40)
  - Mexico (Print Box 25) (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous buildings--no negatives (Print Box 26) (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous buildings--homes, schools, colleges (Print Boxes 27-28) (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous buildings--churches, etc. (Print Boxes 27-28) (Box 41)
  - Miscellaneous copies (Print Box 29) (Box 41)
  - Miscellaneous prints (Print Box 30) (Box 41)
  - Miscellaneous prints (cont.) (Print Box 30) (Box 42)
  - Musicians (Print Box 31) (Box 42)
  - Old-fashioned subjects (Print Box 32) (Box 42)
  - Pittman Moore Co. (Print Box 33) (Box 42)
  - Portraits, groups (Print Box 34) (Box 42)
  - Portraits, individuals (Print Boxes 35-36) (Box 43)
  - Prints for publishers (Print Box 37) (Box 43)
  - Prints for publishers (cont.) (Print Box 37) (Box 44)
  - Prints from miniature negatives (Print Box 38) (Box 44)
  - South Carolina (Print Box 39) (Box 44)
  - Southern trip with H. Miller (Print Box 40) (Box 44)
  - Street scenes (Print Box 41) (Box 44)
  - Water mills (Print Box 42) (Box 45)
  - Winter scenes (Print Box 43) (Box 45)
  - Winter scenes, no negatives (Print Box 43) (Box 46)
  - Brown murder case (Print Box 44) (Box 46)
  - Christian Church, Nashville, IN (Print Box 45) (Box 46)
  - Cuba, '41 (Print Box 46) (Box 46)
  - Mardi Gras (Print Box 47) (Box 46)
  - Nashville Realty (Print Box 48) (Box 46)
  - Navy (Print Box 49) (Box 46)
  - New England, '51 (Print Box 50) (Box 46)
  - New Mexico, '42 (Print Box 51) (Box 46)
  - North Carolina, '39 (Print Box 52) (Box 46)
  - S.E. States '47 (Print Box 53) (Box 47)
  - Thomson estate (Print Box 54) (Box 47)
  - Prints by other photographers (Print Box 55) (Box 47)
  - Non-photographic (Print box 56) (Box 47)
- "Reproductions used for Byrd's book on Hohenberger", 4 Folders (Box 48)
- "Cuts for booklets" (Box 49)
- "Row of Boys at Byron Huff's" (5 x 7) (Ovflat 18)